Finding Aid for School of Nursing (University of Michigan) records, 1891-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Nursing (University of Michigan) records
1891-2010
1940-1993
University of Michigan. School of Nursing.
Established in 1891 as the University of Michigan Training School for Nurses, the School of Nursing offers undergraduate, graduate, and doctoral degrees and continuing education in nursing specializations including medical-surgical nursing, psychiatric mental health nursing, and nursing administration. The record group includes administrative and topical files of the dean, committee and faculty records, photographs, and research area files.
87320 Bimu C276 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
85.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
1.24 GB
The record group was received from the School of Nursing (Donor no. 6818 ) in a series of accessions beginning in January 1983. Personnel records were received in August 1982. The most recent accession was added in 2006.
The School of Nursing records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files including search, review, promotion, and tenure files which are restricted for thirty years from date of creation and student educational records which are restricted for seventy-five years from the date of creation.
In addition, records of the School of Nursing added to the record group after January 1, 2001 are restricted for twenty years from date of accession in accordance with the university's policy on the records of Executive Officers, Deans, Directors and their support offices. Records in this category are identified with an "ER restricted" note.
The University of Michigan School of Nursing record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 35, 73
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 35, 73
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 36-87
Professional nursing education began in the United States in 1873. By 1900 there were 432 schools of nursing operating nationwide. This national trend came to Ann Arbor in 1891 when the University of Michigan Training School for Nurses was organized. The nursing program was established by the Medical School, in large part so that qualified nurses could be found to staff a newly erected University Hospital building.
The connection between the hospital and the nursing program was recognized in 1912, when the school for nurses was reorganized and placed under the direct control of the University Hospital. In 1928 the program's official title was belatedly changed to University Hospital School of Nursing of the University of Michigan. In 1941 the Regents established the nursing program as an independent university teaching unit, the University of Michigan School of Nursing. Although recognized as independent, the school's senior administrative officer was not given the title of dean until 1955.
The original curriculum for the school consisted of a two-year, non-degree program. In 1902 the Regents extended the basic curriculum to three years. In 1915 the first full-time instructor was hired, and in 1919 a second, five-year program, leading to the conferring of a university degree was established. In 1944 it was agreed that the combined course in the liberal arts and nursing should be phased out, in favor of a new program, leading to a bachelor of science in nursing degree.
In 1952 the curriculum was radically revised. The three-year program was discontinued and replaced by a four-year program leading to a BSN. In 1961 the curriculum was expanded to include the school's first masters degree, in psychiatric nursing. The next year, 1962, a masters degree program in medical-surgical nursing was begun. The four-year program, as well as the two master degree programs, received full accreditation, through the National League for Nursing, in 1963. In 1967 the school once again extensively revised its curriculum, with the reforms being placed in effect in 1968. In 1967 the school also launched a major continuing education program for practicing nurses, funded through the Michigan Association for Regional Medical Programs. In the early 1970s the school expanded its degree programs by offering, for the first time, a research-based Ph.D. in Nursing.
At its founding the school was limited to a student body of eight. This number expanded gradually. In 1912 there were about 100 students. Entrance requirements established by the turn of the century specified that students must be women, between the ages of 22 and 32, of superior education and refinement. Specific educational achievements for admission were not imposed until 1915, when possession of a high school diploma was made mandatory. In 1926 it was agreed that incoming nursing students should meet the same admission criteria as students entering the College of Literature, Science and the Arts. It was also agreed, in 1926, that nursing students would receive their basic science instruction through the Medical School. Student comfort, and the nursing program's prestige, were both increased in 1923 with the announcement of a $600,000 gift from Senator James Couzens for the construction of a nurses residence, Couzens Hall. The school's capabilities were dramatically increased in 1958 with the opening of a separate building for the school of nursing, constructed as a part of the Medical Science I complex. By 1970 the school had approximately 1,000 students, one of the largest enrollments in the nation.
The tenure of Dean Rhetaugh Dumas (1981-1994), the school's first African-American dean, brought a number of organizational and curricular changes in the School of Nursing. The Center for Nursing Research was established in 1982 to serve as the central coordinating body for faculty research and to foster collaborative relationships with other units and institutions involved in related research. New programs were developed in Gerontological Nursing, Nurse-Midwifery, Occupational Health Nursing, and Home Health Care. Existing programs, including Nursing Administration, Psychiatric Mental Health Nursing, and the undergraduate studies curriculum, were completely revamped. In 1990, the school's once autonomous academic areas were realigned to form three academic divisions: the Division of Acute, Critical and Long-Term Care, which included Medical-Surgical Nursing and Psychiatric Mental Health Nursing; the Division of Health Promotion and Risk Reduction Programs, which included Community Health Nursing and Parent-Child Nursing; and the Division of Nursing Business and Health Systems Programs, which included Nursing Administration.
Diversity and increased visibility on the university campus were central priorities of the school during Dean Dumas' tenure. The Office of Minority Affairs (later renamed the Office of Multicultural Affairs) was established in the 1980s to focus on the recruitment and retention of students, faculty and staff of color. Dumas was highly active in university affairs, serving on a number of presidential and university task forces and committees related to health affairs and issues affecting women and people of color. This visibility enabled the school to request and receive university funding resources to a greater degree than ever before. After years of lobbying and planning, the School of Nursing moved into renovated space at 400 North Ingalls, part of the former St. Joseph's Hospital, in 1989, the first time in many years that the entire school had been housed together.
Deans of the School of Nursing
1891-1892 Jane Pettigrew
1892-1893 M.E. Davis
1893-1896 Alice Padfield
1896-1898 Anna Harrison
1898-1899 Amy Miller
1899-1901 Grace Ellsworth
1901-1903 Helen Balcom
1903-1906 Ida Tracy
1906-1909 Mary C. Haarer
1909-1910 Ann E. Whitley
1910-1911 Luella Bristol
1911-1913 Elizabeth Holt
1913-1915 Jane M. Pindell
1915-1918 Fantine C. Pemberton
1918-1922 Mary A. Welsh
1922-1923 Louise Gliem
1923-1925 Alice Lake
1925-1930 Shirley C. Titus
1930-1940 Marian Durell
1940-1972 Rhoda Russell
1972-1973 Norma E. Marshall (acting dean)
1973-1975 Carolyne K. Davis
1975-1976 Maxine Loomis (acting dean)
1976-1980 Mary Lohr
1981-1994 Rhetaugh G. Dumas
1994 - Ada S. Hinshaw
Summary Contents List
Dean Rhoda Russell, 1891-1972 -- Boxes 1-21 Committee and Faculty Records, 1931-1972 -- Boxes 1-7 Committee Records, 1931-1972 -- Boxes 1-5 Curriculum, 1947-1971 -- Boxes 1-3 Executive, 1941-1972 -- Box 3 Search (Dean), 1970-1971 -- Box 4 Faculty Records, 1937-1972 -- Boxes 6-7 Meeting Minutes, 1937-1972 -- Boxes 6-7 Topical File, 1891-1972 -- Boxes 7-21 Michigan Association for Regional Medical Programs, 1966-1973 -- Boxes 11-12 Michigan League of Nursing, 1950-1963 -- Box 13 Michigan State Nurses Association, 1946-1962 -- Box 14 National League of Nursing (Accreditation), 1939-1970 -- Boxes 14-17
Dean Carolyne K. Davis and Successors, 1968-1980 -- Boxes 21-30 Committee and Faculty Records, 1970-1980 -- Boxes 21-25 Committee Records, 1970-1980 -- Boxes 21-24 Curriculum, 1972-1978 -- Box 21 Executive, 1972-1979 -- Boxes 21-22 Faculty Records, 1972-1974 -- Boxes 24-25 Meeting Minutes, 1972-1974 -- Box 25 Topical File, 1968-1980 -- Boxes 25-30 National League of Nursing (Accreditation) Curriculum, 1973, 1977 -- Box 28
1985-1990 ACCESSION, 1950-1990 -- Boxes 30-32 Committee Records, 1977-1985 -- Box 30 Executive, 1979-1985 -- Box 30 Space Needs (Emergency), 1976-1977 -- Box 30 Faculty Records, 1974-1989 -- Boxes 30-31 Directories, 1982-1985 -- Box 30 Meeting Minutes, 1974-1990 -- Boxes 30-31 Research Interest Surveys, 1968-1988 -- Box 31 Topical Files, 1950-1988 -- Box 32
Photographs, 1900-1976 -- Box 32 and outsize folder
Mary Ann Swain, Research Area Chair, 1965-1986 -- Boxes 33-34 Topical Files, 1965-1986 -- Boxes 33-34
Dean Rheataugh Dumas Committee Records, 1974-1999 (bulk 1981-1993) -- Boxes 36-44 Standing Committees -- Boxes 36-34 Administrative Council -- Boxes 36-37 Executive Committee -- Boxes 38-41 Task Forces and Special Committees -- Box 43 Faculty Records -- Boxes 45-46 Faculty Meetings -- Boxes 45-46 Topical Files, 1961-1999 (bulk 1981-1993) -- Boxes 47-68 National League for Nursing Accreditation -- Box 61 Speeches -- Boxes 65-66 Facilities Files -- Boxes 69-71
Dean Ada Sue Hinshaw Health Services Research Initiative Task Force -- Box 72
Restricted Files -- Boxes 35, 73
The records of the School of Nursing measure 71.5 feet, with an additional 9 feet of material in records center storage. The records date from 1891 to 1999, although the great majority of the material was created after 1940 by the current School of Nursing. Only fragmentary records of the school's two predecessor units are found in the collection. Reflecting the source of the material, the collection has been arranged into broad subgroups, the titles of which usually reflect the dean from whose office the records originated.
Subjects:
Affirmative action programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; African Americans--Michigan.; Children--Health and hygiene--Michigan.; Medicine--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Association for Regional Medical Programs.; Michigan League of Nursing.; Michigan State Nurses Association.; Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nursing--Research.; Public health.; Psychiatry.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan--Buildings.Buildings.; University of Michigan. Medical Center.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; University of Michigan--Student housing.Student housing.; Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.StudentsSocial life and customs.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.
Contributors:
Davis, Carolyne K.; Lohr, Mary.; Loomis, Maxine E.; Marshall, Norma E.; Ravitz, Mel, 1924-; Russell, Rhoda Reddig, d. 1985.; Swain, Mary Ann Price, 1941-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Dean Rhoda Russell, 1891-1972
  The records of Dean Rhoda Russell (1891-1972) have been divided into two series, Committee and Faculty Records (1931-1972) and a Topical File (1891-1972). Committee and Faculty Records have been further divided into two subseries, Committee Records (1931-1972) and Faculty Records (1937-1972).
  - Committee and Faculty Records, 1931-1972
    Committee Records, arranged alphabetically by committee name, are particularly strong for the 1950s. Included in the subseries are annual committee reports (1951-1964/65) and extensive records of the Curriculum Committee and its many sub-committees (1947-1971). Committee documentation for the 1960s is very weak. Faculty Records, arranged alphabetically by subject, are most interesting for an almost complete run of faculty meeting minutes, 1937-1972. As in the committee records, documentation for the 1960s is very limited. For example, there are no faculty minutes for academic years 1962/63 or 1965/66
    - Committee Records, 1931-1972
      - Administrative Advisory Committee
        - 1941-1955 (Box 1)
        - 1959-1961 (Box 1)
        - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
        - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
        - 1970/71 (Box 1)
      - Admissions, Board of
        - 1951/52 (Box 1)
        - 1952/53 (Box 1)
        - 1953/54 (Box 1)
        - 1954/55 (Box 1)
        - 1955/56 (Box 1)
        - 1956/57 (Box 1)
        - 1957/58 (Box 1)
        - 1958/59 (Box 1)
        - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
      - Annual Reports (of all Committees)
        - 1951-1953 (Box 1)
        - 1953/54 (Box 1)
        - 1954/55 (Box 1)
        - 1955/56 (Box 1)
        - 1956/57 (Box 1)
        - 1957/58 (Box 1)
        - 1958/59 (Box 1)
        - 1959/60, 1964/65 (Box 1)
      - Basic Science Committee, 1953-1955 (Box 1)
        (see also Box 2)
      - Committees, 1971/72 (Box 1)
      - Content Committee
        - 1954/55 (Box 1)
        - 1955/56 (Box 1)
      - Curriculum Committee
        - Full Committee
          - 1947-1951 (Box 1)
          - 1951/52 (Box 1)
          - 1952/53 (Box 1)
          - 1953/54 (Box 1)
          - 1954/55 (Box 2)
          - 1955/56 (Box 2)
          - 1956/57 (Box 2)
          - 1957/58 (Box 2)
          - 1958/59 (Box 2)
          - 1959/60 (Box 2)
          - 1963/64-1964/65 (Box 2)
          - 1969/70 (Box 2)
          - 1970/71 (Box 2)
        - Subcommittees
          - Subcommittee 1 (Freshman Year)
            - 1952/53 (Box 2)
            - 1953/54 (Box 2)
            - 1954/55 (Box 2)
            - 1955/56 (Box 2)
            - 1956/57 (Box 2)
            - 1957/58 (Box 2)
            - 1958/59 (Box 2)
          - Subcommittee 2 (Sophomore Year)
            - 1952/53 (Box 2)
            - 1953/54 (Box 2)
            - 1954/55 (Box 2)
            - 1955/56 (Box 2)
            - 1956/57 (Box 2)
            - 1957/58 (Box 2)
            - 1958/59 (Box 2)
          - Subcommittee 3 (Junior Year)
            - 1952/53 (Box 2)
            - 1953/54 (Box 2)
            - 1954/55 (Box 2)
            - 1955/56 (Box 2)
            - 1956/57 (Box 2)
            - 1957/58 (Box 2)
            - 1958/59 (Box 2)
          - Subcommittee 4 (Senior Year)
            - 1952/53 (Box 2)
            - 1953/54 (Box 2)
            - 1954/55 (Box 2)
            - 1955/56 (Box 2)
            - 1956/57 (Box 2)
            - 1957/58 (Box 2)
            - 1958/59 (Box 2)
          - Basic Science Curriculum Subcommittee, 1951/52-1954/55 (Box 2)
          - General Nursing Curriculum Subcommittee
            - 1950/51 (Box 2)
            - 1951/52 (Box 3)
            - 1952/53 (Box 3)
            - 1954/55 (Box 3)
            - 1959/60 (Box 3)
          - Planning Curriculum Subcommittee, 1952/53-1953/54 (Box 3)
          - Public Health Curriculum Subcommittee, 1952/53 (Box 3)
      - Curriculum Conference Committee, 1955 (Box 3)
      - Curriculum Study Group, 1958-1961 (Box 3)
      - Data Form for Faculty Applicants, 1958/59 (Box 3)
      - Educational Psychology Committee, 1952-1960 (Box 3)
      - Evaluations Committee
        - 1931-1952 (Box 3)
        - 1952/53-1954/55 (Box 3)
        - 1955/56 (Box 3)
        - 1956/57 (Box 3)
        - 1957/58 (Box 3)
        - 1958/59 (Box 3)
        - 1959/60 (Box 3)
        - 1961/62 (Box 3)
      - Executive Committee
        - 1941-1951 (Box 3)
        - 1951-1953 (Box 3)
        - 1952-1957 (Box 3)
        - 1957-1960 (Box 3)
        - (Membership Lists), 1960-1972 (Box 3)
        - 1961-1964 (Box 3)
        - 1964-1967 (Box 3)
        - 1968/69 (Box 3)
        - 1970/71 (Box 3)
        - 1971/72 (Box 3)
      - Four Year Academic Year Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 3)
      - Graduate Education Committee (Box 4)
        - 1959-1961 (Box 4)
        - 1963-1966 (Box 4)
      - Graduate Education-Psychology Committee, 1960-1963 (Box 4)
      - Hospital and Nurse Service Survey, 1945/46 (Box 4)
      - Improvement of Patient Care Committee, 1959 (Box 4)
      - Learning Experiences Away from the Medical Center (Committee of Six), 1957-1960 (Box 4)
      - Library Committee, 1951-1960 (Box 4)
      - Methods of Teaching Committee, 1954/55 (Box 4)
      - Operating Room Committee, 1957-1959 (Box 4)
      - Pediatric Building Committee, 1955 (Box 4)
      - Physical Growth and Development Committee, 1957-1964 (Box 4)
      - Procedure Committee
        - 1954/55 (Box 4)
        - 1955/56 (Box 4)
        - 1956/57 (Box 4)
        - 1957/58 (Box 4)
        - 1958/59 (Box 4)
        - 1959/60 (Box 4)
      - Professional Education and Experience Committee, 1963-1966 (Box 4)
      - Public Health Committee
        - Advisory Committee
          - 1937-1949 (Box 4)
          - 1950-1958 (Box 4)
          - 1961-1962 (Box 4)
        - Michigan Coordinating Committee, 1961 (Box 4)
        - Study Committee, 1957 (Box 4)
      - Recruitment Committee, 1949-1960 (Box 4)
      - Scholastic Standing Committee
        - 1966-1970 (Box 4)
        - 1971-1973 (Box 4)
      - Search Committee (New Dean), 1970-1971; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Search Committee (New Dean) (cont.), 1970-1971 (Box 5)
      - Social Committee, 1954-1966 (Box 5)
      - Steering Committee
        - 1954/55 (Box 5)
        - 1955/56 (Box 5)
        - 1957/58 (Box 5)
        - 1958/59 (Box 5)
      - Student Faculty Committee, 1951-1958 (Box 5)
      - Student Personnel Study Committee, 1955-1957 (Box 5)
      - Student Uniform Committee, 1954/55 (Box 5)
      - Task Committee, 1950; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - University Committees
        - Council of Big Ten Universities, 1957 (Box 5)
        - Economic Status of the Faculty, 1961-1963 (Box 5)
        - Faculty Club Committee, 1960-1966 (Box 5)
        - Honors Convocation Committee, 1951-1956 (Box 5)
        - Improvement of Instruction Committee, 1960-1963 (Box 5)
        - Nursing Education Needs in Michigan, 1967-1971 (Box 5)
        - Status of Women Committee, 1949/50 (Box 5)
        - University Hospital Committee
          - Board in Control, 1948 (Box 5)
          - Advisory and Study Committee
            - Full Committee, 1966-1968 (Box 5)
            - Task Force III, 1967-1968; 3 folders (Box 5)
        - University Planning Committee, 1963-1966 (Box 5)
        - University Policies in the Teaching and Organization of the Health Related Professions, Report, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Faculty Records, 1937-1972
      - Activity Study, 1971 (Box 6)
      - Evaluation Conference, 1960/61 (Box 6)
      - Instruction Records, Correspondence, 1957-1960 (Box 6)
      - Meeting Minutes
        - 1937-1946 (Box 6)
        - 1947-1948 (Box 6)
        - 1949-July 1951 (Box 6)
        - 1951-1952 (Box 6)
        - 1952/53 (Box 6)
        - 1953/54 (Box 6)
        - 1954/55 (Box 6)
        - 1955/56 (Box 6)
        - 1956/57 (Box 6)
        - 1957/58 (Box 6)
        - 1958/59 (Box 6)
        - 1959/60 (Box 6)
        - 1960/61 (Box 6)
        - 1961/62 (Box 6)
        - 1963/64 (Box 6)
        - 1964/65 (Box 6)
        - 1966/67 (Box 6)
        - 1967/68 (Box 6)
        - 1968-1969 (Box 7)
        - 1969/70 (Box 7)
        - 1970/71, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - 1971/72 (Box 7)
      - Workshops
        - 1954-1955 (Box 7)
        - 1957 (Box 7)
        - 1958 (Box 7)
        - 1959 (Box 7)
        - 1960-1961 (Box 7)
        - 1962 (Box 7)
        - 1963 (Box 7)
        - 1964 (Box 7)
        - 1965 (Box 7)
  - Topical File, 1891-1972
    Dean Russell's Topical File, which is also arranged alphabetically, contains all of the surviving documentation for the School of Nursing's predecessor units, as well as material generated during Dean Russell's term of office. Material about predecessor units is found primarily in the following file headings: History; Michigan State Government, Board of Nursing, Reports; New York State Nursing Reports; and Reports, School of Nursing, Annual. Regarding Dean Russell's own period of service, the Topical File is particularly informative regarding accreditation (filed under the National League of Nursing, the agency responsible for accreditation), curriculum changes, graduate programs, the Michigan Association for Regional Medical Programs, the Michigan League of Nursing, the Michigan State Nurses Association and the student body (filed both under Students, as well as Alumnae and Alumni, Class Lists).
    Because of the span of years involved, filing practices vary greatly in the Topical File. Sometimes material was gathered together under a general heading with several subheadings (such as the Michigan Association for Regional Medical Programs) while in other cases material is scattered throughout (one example is student material). Furthermore, similar, but not necessarily related, materials were often filed under the same heading. Efforts have been made in processing to correct such problems, but undoubtedly several remain undetected.
    - Adams, James P., 1945-1947 (Box 7)
    - Administrative Staff, 1959/60 (Box 7)
    - Admissions, 1970-1972 (Box 7)
    - Affiliations, 1943-1959 (Box 7)
    - Alumnae Association
      - 1914- circa 1945 (Box 7)
      - 1948-1954 (Box 7)
      - 1957-1961 (Box 7)
    - Alumnae Correspondence, 1955-1961 (Box 7)
    - Alumnae Council, 1949-1952 (Box 7)
    - Alumnae Day Programs
      - 1960-1961 (Box 7)
      - 1963 (Box 7)
      - 1964 (Box 7)
    - Alumnae, Deceased or Non-Graduates, 1893-1947 (Box 7)
    - Alumni Society (Medical Center)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 7)
      - 1963 (Box 7)
      - 1966-1968 (Box 8)
    - Alumni Surveys (School of Nursing)
      - 1956 (Box 8)
      - 1956-1961 (Box 8)
      - 1969-1971 (Box 8)
    - Anatomy and Physiology, 1955-1965 (Box 8)
    - Appeal Procedure, Academic Staff, 1970-1972 (Box 8)
    - Appointment and Promotion Process, 1970-1971 (Box 8)
    - Arnstein, Margaret (U.S. Public Health Service), 1955-1958 (Box 8)
    - Arthritis Center Proposal, 1969 (Box 8)
    - Association of Collegiate Schools, 1931-1948 (Box 8)
    - Association of Deans (American Association of Deans of College and University Schools of Nursing), 1971 (Box 8)
    - Battle Creek Community Hospital, 1956-1961 (Box 8)
    - Beal Residence, 1946-1954 (Box 8)
    - Bio-Chemistry (Dr. Lila Miller), 1940-1962 (Box 8)
    - Black Students and Faculty, Recruitment and Report of Advisor to, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Board of Regents
      - General, 1891-1961 (Box 8)
      - Four Year Degree Program, 1952 (Box 8)
    - Bridgman, Margaret (National League of Nursing, NLN), 1957-1958 (Box 8)
    - Broadcasting Service, 1944-1964 (Box 8)
    - Budget
      - 1953-1960 (Box 8)
      - 1960-1965 (Box 8)
      - 1968-1972 (Box 8)
    - Bureau of Appointments and Occupational Information, 1956 (Box 8)
    - Bureau of Psychological Services, Undated (Box 8)